NARRATOR: The future...
The polar ice caps
have melted,
covering the earth with water.
Those who survived
have adapted
to a new world.
(GARGLING)
(METAL CLANGING)
(WHISTLES)
(SPEAKING HINDl)
Bad luck, English.
But the Slavers are producing
a good grade of poxy these days.
Cost you a handful of dirt
or maybe that wind chime.
What are you doing here?
Just waiting.
Take your hand off the sail.
Take it off!
I've seen your boat before.
Haven't seen you.
Took it legal.
Previous owner was dead
on the tiller when I found it.
You had another hour
before I traded up again.
Just improving my means.
Well, I owe you then.
No, thanks.
I got all the supplies I need.
Just came from an atoll.
Eight days east,
if you're interested.
Two Drifters meet, something
needs to be exchanged.
I know the code. But I'll
give you this one for free.
Nothing's free in Waterworld.
Yeah.
(MOTORS WHIRRING)
Smokers.
Just enough wind
to get away clean.
DRIFTER: Forget the bag.
It's not worth it. You'll never
make it with your sails down.
Hey!
(MIMICKING GOBBLING)
What can I say?
(LAUGHS)
Joe, he's going for it.
What the hell?
Never seen that before.
Here we go! Go!
Drive! Drive!
Faster! Faster!
(WHOOPING)
Come on! He's gonna get it!
He's gonna get it!
Go!
Get him! Get him!
(CONTINUES SHOUTING)
(GRUMBLES ANGRILY)
No! No!
(GRUNTING)
(SMOKERS SHOUTING)
(MACHINE GUNS FIRING)
(DRIFTER GROANS)
(DRIFTER SCREAMS IN PAIN)
MAN: Inbound! Straight out
from the gates.
(SPEAKING PORTUGREEK)
English.
Flag's down, Drifter.
We got enough traders.
(PEOPLE MURMURING)
WOMAN: What does he have?
Dirt.
Open the gates!
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
MAN: Bones to berries.
Veins to vine.
These tendons to trees.
This blood to brine.
Too old she was.
This woman does leave us,
recycled and enshrined
in the presence of him
who leads us.
(CHILDREN CHATTERING)
(BOYS WHINING)
BOY: What is that?
You know me?
I know what you are.
Good.
Then you know if you look
for trouble while you're here,
you'll find more than
you can handle.
You got two hours.
I'll only need one.
He's coming over here.
Me.
You each get one
if everything's here
when I get back.
Pure dirt.
(OTHERS EXCLAIMING)
3.2 kilos.
How'd you come by
so much of it?
Another atoll 30 horizons
west of here.
Where'd they get it?
They didn't say.
MAN 1: We heard about that place,
that they was all killed.
That's why they didn't say. Smokers?
Maybe Smokers, maybe Slavers.
So what's the word?
We trading or not?
We'll tally it
like pure hydro.
Works out to 62 chits.
I want twice that.
(PEOPLE MURMURING)
HYDROHOLIC: I just want
one sip of hydro!
NORD: No, not till you tell me.
She got inkings on her back.
I seen her.
They say if you read
the marks on the child,
they'll lead you
all the way to Dryland.
Dryland's a myth.
Some still believe.
They say the Smokers
even got an eye out for her.
Well, then, we'd better
keep it to ourselves.
Help you?
Yeah.
Where's the store?
You found it.
You don't have much.
You the man with the dirt?
Skoal.
One more.
Make it two.
A man this rich will buy for
a fellow outwater, I'm sure.
One.
That's an interesting
pair of boots you got.
Trade?
No.
NORD: Shame.
That's her.
HELEN: Enola.
Hey, what are you doing?
No, you can't do that.
I need another piece.
I want to draw some more.
I'll give it to you.
Just stay in the back.
With all those chits,
you could order up a bath.
Have you ever had a freshwater
bath? Why are you talking to me?
Just being friendly.
Is that a tomato plant?
Yeah.
You have a keen eye.
Saw one in a picture.
How much?
Half your chits.
I'll take them, too.
Take what?
You bought everything.
I'll take them shelves.
So, what did you see out there
in your 15 months?
Such as?
An end to all this water.
Asking the wrong person.
BOY: Where did he come from?
The one they buried today? Uh-huh.
She found the only end
there is.
I've got a proposition
for you, Mariner.
I'm not staying.
We're not asking you to.
All we want is your seed.
ELDER: We can look to our own
for impregnation,
but too much of that sort
of thing gets undesirable.
When she's pregnant,
you go on your way with
all the supplies you need.
You don't have anything.
You're dying.
No man stays out that long
and turns down a woman.
He's hiding something.
Maybe he's a Smoker spy.
(WHISTLING)
When the elders say so,
you can leave, and not before.
(GRUNTING)
Gills.
Mutation!
He's a mutant!
(PEOPLE SHOUTING)
MAN: (GROANING) My hand!
(SCREAMING)
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
MAN 2: Throw the nets!
MAN 3: He's a murderer!
(GRUNTING)
By what right...
You pay me to keep the peace.
This isn't it.
No!
He has killed one of ours.
He was defending himself.
He needs to be destroyed!
Kill him. Let's kill him. That may be,
but not here
and not like this.
BOY 1: What is it?
BOY 2: Damn.
They're too tight.
I can't get it off.
Open the gate.
(HUMMING)
Is it a map?
You'd tell me if you knew,
wouldn't you, Enola?
Mmm-hmm.
What are you drawing?
I don't know.
Helen, look. Look at the
prodigal child's latest vision.
(CHUCKLES)
How soon
before we can leave?
I don't have any idea yet
where we can go.
I haven't figured out
the tattoo on her back.
I'm a stupid man.
The answer's right there.
It's just beyond me.
Maybe he knows.
Yes, I see. They are webbed.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, ten digits. That's wonderful.
They tell me, too, that you
have gills. Isotropic gills.
Are they merely vestigial
or are they functional?
My name is Gregor. I've just
come to pay you a little...
Oh, my God.
(GREGOR LAUGHING)
I'm sorry. I'm not laughing
at you. I'm excited.
Your gills,
they're functional.
Ichthyus sapien.
You can breathe in the water.
How deep can you go?
Look, I'm only here because I
want to learn more about you.
You don't like humans
very much, do you?
I can't say that I blame you.
But tell me, are all of your
kind as bad-tempered as you are?
I have no kind.
Oh, fish rot.
I'd be surprised if there weren't
others, and if there aren't,
there will be eventually.
Anyway, I've come here because
I need to ask you a question.
Where did your dirt come from?
Is it from Dryland?
Do you know what this is?
The ancients, they did
something terrible, didn't they?
To cause all this water.
Hundreds, hundreds of years ago.
If I tell you,
will you open this lock?
I haven't a key.
There's a mooring
cleat down there. What?
Good as any key.
A mooring cleat?
I won't hurt anyone.
I'll just leave.
I'll be right back.
MAN: Gregor!
What's your business there?
Move along!
I'm not a brave man.
If you know anything about
Dryland, please tell me. Please!
Don't let it die with you.
No, no, no, no. Stop!
MAN: Gregor! Move along!
ELDER: After considerable
deliberation of the evidence at hand,
it is our decision that this mute-o
does, indeed, constitute a threat.
Therefore, in the interest
of public safety,
he is hereby sentenced
to be recycled
in the customary fashion.
Proceed.
I'm sorry.
Bones to berries.
Veins to vines.
These tendons to trees.
This blood to brine.
Too strange for life he was.
This mute-o now does leave us,
recycled and entombed,
in the presence of him
who leads us.
Smokers! Get out of the sun!
To your posts!
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
WOMAN: Oh, my God!
Oh, my God!
Kill!
There!
(SHOUTING)
We are safe behind this wall.
Aren't we?
Let me out!
Let me out! I'll fight!
(SMOKERS SHOUTING)
Give me the key
to the city now.
Let's go! Let's go! Let's go!
SMOKER 1: Floor it! Floor it!
SMOKER 2: Come on!
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
Swab it! Swab it!
God damn! More ammo!
SMOKER: Break down the door!
(SCREAMS)
My God!
(GRUNTING)
We'll have this atoll
in no time.
Crank it! Crank it!
Look!
MAN: Look out!
(GRUNTS)
Oh, no!
Keep that gas going!
Fill them up!
Helen, come quickly!
Helen! Helen!
(MEN GRUNTING)
You're not supposed to go yet!
Infernal machine!
Gregor. Gregor, wait!
Helen, I tried. There was an accident.
I couldn't make it stop. Hurry!
You can make it if you
try. Run! Pease, stop!
Up those stairs.
Run! Quickly!
Wait! Wait! I'll throw
you a rope. Run quickly!
Throw the rope now. Run, Enola.
ENOLA: Slow down! Wait!
No! No!
Wait!
Gregor, don't leave us!
Oh, no!
I'm sorry!
It was an accident!
Helen! Enola!
Helen, I'm sorry!
Shoot him. Shoot him.
If I let you out of here,
you're taking us with you.
Sure.
HELEN: Enola, get down.
Here. Get over here.
Get down.
Hurry! Come on!
Get the gate.
(GUNS FIRING)
(GRUNTING)
Hurry up!
Kamikaze! Come on!
That made a hole.
Find her! Get the girl!
There!
Go get that guy!
Go! Kill him!
Wow!
Enola!
MARINER: You're too slow!
Run to the other side.
Come on!
Grab on! Hold on, hold on.
It's stuck!
I can't make it through!
Let her go!
Just drop her!
Turn the wheel.
The wheel! Turn it!
That! Come on! Push it!
I am!
Hurry! Now pull!
Push it! Push it hard!
Push it!
Okay, okay! Now pull this!
Pull this! Go! Go!
Pull it! Pull!
Enola, jump.
Jump! Look at me. Jump! Now!
Okay!
Well, excuse me!
Did I say anybody could leave
before the battle was over? Did I?
No! No! Well, do
something. I hate sails.
Hey! Can you steer?
Can I trust you?
(ROPE CREAKING WITH TENSION)
Answer me this, somebody.
Why is that boat still firing?
What's that cousin's name?
Chuck.
Hey, Chuck! He's pulling
him right into us.
Maybe he doesn't answer to
Chuck. Call him Charles. Charles!
Stop him! Stop him!
Charles!
Adios, cousins.
She's here somewhere.
Keep looking.
Stop it!
WOMAN: Let me down!
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
What you got?
Couple of heartbeats over
there. Aren't saying much.
If you'll notice the arterial nature of
the blood coming from the hole in my head,
you can assume that we're
all having a real lousy day.
So here it is, I need to
know about that tattooed girl.
First one
that tells me lives.
I saw a girl. I saw... It was...
She had a big tattoo on her.
You won. Start over.
I saw a girl.
I'm not sure, but I think she
got on that boat with three hulls.
The boat that cost me
1,000 G's of go-juice?
Yeah, the mute-o's boat.
Mute-o?
Yeah. He got these slits here.
Like fish gills.
He wasn't really a man.
A fluke of evolution.
Oh, I'm sorry. A fluke of...
Evolution.
I know!
No! No, you said you wouldn't
kill me! Did I say that?
Witnesses, anybody, did I?
Yes, yes, yes! You said...
You said it.
Oh, I may have.
I may have.
(SCREAMING)
We get to the 'Deez,
tank up that sky boat,
send it out on patrol.
We gotta keep an eye out
for that ichthy-freak.
You been there, haven't you?
Dryland?
You know where it is.
Yeah, I know where it is.
And... And we're going?
You and I are.
The kid we gotta pitch
over the side.
What?
My boat's tore up.
I'm taking on water.
I'd be lucky to get half
a hydro ration out of that.
You know...
I said I won't drink.
For 12 days?
No. It's better one of you dies
now than both of you die slow.
Wait. Wait.
We saved your life.
We got you out.
No, you got me out so you
could get out. We're even.
She can cook. She can fish.
So can I. Then take my
necklace. Take my necklace.
I got better ones below.
No, look!
After what you went through
back there on the atoll,
I can understand
why you would want to.
But she's a child.
(HUMMING)
Is there something else, then?
Enola! Go below.
Enola.
Yeah.
You said so yourself.
Been out there a long time.
Couple hours ago,
I was potential dirt to you.
We're not like that.
You all are.
Know what I was
really thinking?
Why I don't drop both of you
in my wake right now.
You got nothing I need.
You're taking us to Dryland.
Killing's a hard thing
to do well.
Believe me. I'm not the
one to start on. Both of us!
How long you plan
to hold that on me?
As long as it takes.
Okay.
No!
HELEN: Let me out of here!
Where the hell are you?
Don't you touch my child.
Come here!
(HELEN GRUNTING)
Okay, now,
don't move, okay? There.
Oh, looking real good, yeah.
There. There.
All done.
Now, there may be some small
problem in depth perception.
Well, it better not screw up
my short game.
Well?
Looks good.
I like it. Yeah.
I like it better than
your real eye. Much better.
What do you say, Toby?
The truth. Looks like shit.
That's why I love children.
No guile.
It does look like shit.
And it feels like cold shit!
Deacon?
What...
I'm sorry. It's just that
there's a problem in the pit.
Maybe you should come.
Let's drive.
The pit. Don't bother
with the scenic route.
Drive!
Hey, it's driving better.
Get off!
Get off.
Get out of the way.
All right, all right,
all right. Okay, okay.
Bless you, cousins. Bless you.
Bless all you cousins over there.
Keep up the good work.
Growth is progress.
DEPTH GAUGE GUY:
Somebody! Hey, up there!
Take it off!
Yes.
Your Deaconship.
Hello. Good morning.
Or night, whichever
the case may be.
What is it? I'm a busy man.
I thought you should know.
We're down to exactly
four feet, nine inches
of black stuff.
Thank you, sir.
How many G's is that after
refining? Maybe three refuelers.
We'll burn through that
in two lunars. Sweet Joe!
Will somebody please tell me
what's happening to this place?
We outgrowed it.
All right, the only thing that
is important is the tattooed girl.
We don't spare any go-juice
finding her.
We don't waste it anywhere else.
You cancel all those tractor pulls
and all that stuff
until later.
You got it?
Dryland is the mother lode.
On your toes.
Excellent.
Hi.
Move.
HELEN: Enola! Enola, come here!
Come on!
Enola, come over here.
Hey!
What are you doing? Decorating
your boat. It's ugly.
Where did you get this?
From down below.
This is mine! You don't
touch anything of mine.
I drew it for you.
You don't draw on anything.
You understand?
MARINER: What...
This is my boat.
I got it the way I like it.
You take up space
and you slow me down.
You know,
she's just a little girl.
She doesn't know your
rules. You wanna stay?
You teach her.
HELEN: Enola, what'd I tell you?
You're not so tough.
You know that?
How many people
have you killed?
Ten? Twenty?
You talk a lot. I talk a lot
'cause you don't talk at all.
Now, how many?
Including little girls?
I'm not afraid of you.
I told Helen you wouldn't be
so ugly if you cut your hair.
In fact,
you talk all the time.
It's like a storm when you're around.
HELEN: Enola!
Hey! What are you doing?
Helen! You bastard! She can't swim!
ENOLA: Help me! Helen!
Helen, help me!
Helen!
(GASPING)
Helen! Helen!
Hold on!
Look at me. Look at me.
Look at me.
(GASPING) Oh, please, come back. Please!
Please! Oh, please!
(HELEN COUGHING VIOLENTLY)
HELEN: Hey!
Hold on. Okay, almost.
Thanks. I swear,
if you ever touch her again...
You son of a bitch.
Look at me.
You will go to bed that night
and you will never wake up.
Shut up.
What?
Smokers?
Yeah.
Can't we outrun them?
Not with my sail down.
What are you thinking about?
That's a nice touch.
That's them.
Don't hit the kid.
(LAUGHING DEVILISHLY)
HELEN: Hey!
Coward!
Fuck!
No!
(GROANING)
Joe!
Cut it!
Come on! Come on!
All right. Okay.
HELEN: Oh, I'm really sorry.
I'm sorry. But you didn't
give me much choice.
Oh, I know.
But you ran away. I... What?
What are you...
No! Please, no! No!
(GRUNTING)
Don't ever touch anything
on my boat again.
She said she was sorry!
That means you're supposed
to say something back!
Did you say something?
ENOLA: Mmm-mmm.
DEACON: The child...
Did he have the girl with him?
NORD: Uh-huh.
Seems to me if we launch now, we
can cut him down just about here.
If he doesn't change course.
It's not likely.
He's a wily one,
that ichthy-demon.
Yeah, if he knows
he's been spotted,
he'll expect us to expect
him to change course,
which is exactly
why he'll keep his heading.
The important question is,
where's he heading?
And does he know
how precious his cargo is?
I say that he's headed here,
and we take him here.
DRIFTER: Hello!
Drifter?
Mmm-hmm.
Are we gonna stop?
Look at the flag!
His flag's up.
I thought you all
stopped for each other.
(DRIFTER YELLING)
Well, maybe
he has some food!
Don't find many who follow
the rules anymore.
Well, make it quick.
What's your business?
Trade.
You got any resin?
(CHUCKLING)
Resin? He's gotta be out of his mind. He's
out of his mind. I don't have any resin.
You been outwater a long time,
haven't you?
Must be joking me, man. Resin!
You don't got enough.
How about food?
Could you say that again,
please?
How about food?
Yeah, food.
Yeah, that'd be good, eh?
I haven't eaten in,
well, you know, forever.
Which one of you two is the cook?
'Cause I usually fall for the waitress.
(SNICKERS)
Like you said,
I don't have much.
I'll say. Let's see.
We can start with that wee
orchard you got over there.
(EXCLAIMING)
MARINER: All right, hold it there.
We can talk.
Fair enough.
(MUTTERING)
It's a nice rod, isn't it?
I like that rod.
It's a nice rod.
Got yourself a wee harem
going here, now, don't you, eh?
What do you want
for the women?
We're not for sale.
Not for sale? There's no
such thing as not for sale.
"Not for sale"!
Not for sale, eh?
Are they a pair, or would you
consider selling them separate?
No. Our business
is done here
unless you got some resin
for sale you can part with.
I told you once already,
I don't have it.
Don't have it. Don't have it.
Haven't seen that there for trade in
lunars now. Wait. Wait, wait, wait.
I do have something that'll
make you change your mind.
Something that
you can't pass on.
(SNICKERING)
I took it off
an atoller refugee camp.
The life savings
of the entire clan.
Paper. Look at my wee paper.
It's paper. Have you ever
seen paper? Look at it.
Smell it.
(SNIFFING)
I been saving it
for a special trade.
Don't you do it.
You know, maybe I'm talking
to the wrong person here.
Whose boat is this?
Is it your boat or your boat?
No. No, it's his boat.
But he doesn't own us.
Half an hour.
Is he out of his mind
or something here?
I got two pages in here, man!
I mean, I'd get half a dozen
girls with this, you know.
Half an hour.
You trading or not?
Don't.
Shut up.
Okay.
Forty-five minutes
with the wee one over there.
I like to do the talking,
if you know what I mean.
No!
Fair enough.
Come, come, come, come, come!
No. My boat.
Fair enough. Fair enough.
Good, good, good. Aye.
Helen.
Sit down.
Enola, just do as he says.
(SNICKERING)
It's been a while
for me now.
Guess it's been
more than a while, actually.
I've only got half an hour. Half an
hour, half an hour, half an hour...
Right, right, right...
You're so beautiful. Aye!
Anyone ever told you that?
Give me that. What are you
doing? It's just a game.
Oh, I... I...
We was just playing.
The trade's off.
I changed my mind.
Well, you can't do that.
I mean, a deal's a deal, aye?
I just did.
Hey!
She's mine. Aye. No.
No, no, I won't have it, no.
Go on. Get, get, get.
Go, go, go. Good, good.
But don't go too far, now.
This won't take but a minute.
I hate this boat.
I hate this boat!
You bastard.
You're pretty stingy for a man who's
got everything, aren't you, now?
(CLANGING)
DRIFTER: You bastard!
Where's me boat?
Help me to me boat.
(GROANING) Me boat.
HELEN: What the... No!
Never catch anything
with this. It's useless.
HELEN: Look, I'm sorry.
You were right about the pole.
You were right,
but we have to eat.
Now, I know you can hear me!
Now, we can fish for ourselves.
You show us what to do.
You must know how.
Even you gotta eat!
You just sit there.
What...
I don't know.
(SEA MONSTER ROARING)
(GUN FIRING)
Happy now?
(HUMMING)
You don't like my singing,
do you?
Helen says you don't like my
singing 'cause you can't sing.
Ever try and listen?
To what?
The sound of the world.
I don't hear anything.
That's because you're too loud
and you're moving around
all the time.
Try sitting still.
Eyeball?
I wish I had feet like his.
Then maybe I could swim.
Enola.
(BURPS)
Sorry.
Never met a person
who couldn't swim before.
I can't.
People said I was weird.
Maybe they were right.
Maybe they were right
about you, too.
Enola wanted
to give you this.
And this.
She won't take it again.
You don't look
much like her.
Well, I'm not her mother,
if that's what you're asking.
You act like it.
What are those marks
on her back?
Nothing.
They're just fanciful things.
Like what she draws?
She draws what she sees.
She's like a mirror.
People on the atoll
thought she was a...
Freak?
Yeah.
I just thought
she was special.
I'm not giving it to her.
It's just...
A loan.
Yeah. I'm not
giving it to her.
Is Dryland beautiful?
You'll see.
(ENOLA GIGGLING)
Enola?
Enola, what are you doing?
Those monsters'll kill her!
No, they're asleep now.
Hands around my neck.
Let the water tell your arms
and legs how to move.
We're going down.
Hold your breath.
What is it?
Barter outpost.
You said we'd get
to Dryland today.
Today. Tomorrow.
What's it matter?
I need resin.
(SPEAKING PORTUGREEK)
What is that?
It's PortuGreek.
Their own language.
Or so I thought.
(SNIFFING)
There's my girl. Yeah.
Howdy, darling.
Come on in here now.
What's going on?
Smokers.
What the hell?
He's spotted us. Sound it!
Sound it! Sound it!
(WHOOPING)
HELEN: Enola!
Starboard side! Now!
Get in the chair!
Watch it.
He's clearing the net.
Go to the helm.
Get the centerboard!
Centerboard?
What centerboard?
I don't know what to do!
It's too late. Over here!
(SCREAMING)
No!
Give me that rifle.
Boy, if you wanna do something
right, you've got to do it yourself.
All right.
(GRUNTS)
I winged him.
I say we load all the go-juice onto
one boat and run the freak down.
You can't catch him in ten boats,
and you wanna send just one?
Well, I pray that
you're joking.
Bring me the trackers.
He's hurt.
HELEN: It's not what you
think. They weren't after her.
I saw what I saw.
What?
No more lies.
(SHRIEKING)
What are the marks
on her back?
People say
it's the way to Dryland.
Dryland's a myth!
No! You said so yourself
that you know where it is.
You did.
You're a fool to believe in
something you've never seen before.
I've seen it. I've touched it! Dirt
that was richer and darker than yours.
It was in the basket
we found Enola in!
It doesn't exist! Well,
how can you be so sure?
Because I've sailed farther than most
have dreamed, and I've never seen it.
But the things on your boat!
"Things on my boat" what?
There are things on your boat
that nobody has ever seen!
What are these shells?
And that reflecting glass?
(STUTTERING)
And the music box? That...
Well, if not from Dryland,
then where? Where?
You wanna see Dryland?
You really wanna see it?
I'll take you to Dryland.
Get in.
Well, what about Enola?
There's only air for one.
Get in the water.
It'll be all right.
Don't touch anything.
Okay?
I didn't know.
All this time...
Nobody does.
Can you get us out of here?
DEACON: I'd say there're
two chances of that.
Hey!
No way and no how.
Should've bought me
that drink. Come on!
This way. Come on!
(SMOKERS WHOOPING)
DEACON:
Proper introductions first.
I'm the Deacon.
If you don't recall the face, perhaps
it's 'cause I didn't always look like this.
Now, I suspect
she's somewhere real close.
So we can tear this boat apart
looking for her,
but I'd rather
somebody tell me where she is.
And the first one
that does that lives.
And the runner-up... Well,
actually, there are no runners-up.
Oh, sweet Joe,
I love this part.
Choose them.
One, two. Live or die.
You know, personally,
I'd rather shoot
the sperm-of-the-devil here.
But you know something?
I don't think you're
gonna tell me, are you?
Too bad.
Come on. What do you say?
She's not your kind.
You don't even
have a kind.
If you say it,
he'll still kill us both.
(DEACON GRUNTING)
Let's not get ahead
of ourselves.
If you don't tell me,
I swear to Poseidon
I will torch your boat.
DEACON: Refresh my memory. What
happens when neither of them talks?
Never happened before.
All right!
If they won't tell us
where she is, do them!
Both of them! Kill them now!
No!
HELEN: No!
So gullible! Bring her here.
Take and ye shall receive!
HELEN: No! Leave her!
So ends your daily sermonette!
All we gotta do is figure out
this map. Turn her upside down.
Does that mean anything to you? No.
We'll figure it out back at the
'Deez. Back at the 'Deez, boys.
Careful with her.
Careful with her!
What about them?
Do them both.
Torch the boat.
(GRUNTING)
We have to go under!
No, I can't breathe
like you!
I'll breathe for both of us.
(GUNS FIRING)
ENOLA: Helen!
Helen, help!
Helen! Helen!
My boat.
Enola.
DEACON: What is this?
Get those chains off her.
What are we,
barbarians here?
Goodness gracious.
Sakes alive.
Come on out of here,
you big, nasty animal, you!
Well, rub-a-dub-dub.
You wanna come over here
and sit on my lap?
No?
How about a cigarette?
Nothing like a good smoke
if you miss your mom.
Never too young to start.
No. Well, I got something
right here I know you'd like.
Like to draw, don't you?
Now, they're yours,
if you help me with
just one problem, all right?
Now, that tattoo
on your back...
I've been told that
that's actually a map?
It's the way to Dryland.
Now we're getting someplace.
Could you teach me
how to read that?
Setback.
Well, have you ever heard any
of your friends talk about it?
You know, like your mommy
or your pet fish?
Did he say anything?
You shouldn't make fun of
him. He wouldn't like it.
Girl, I don't give a shit what
he'd like. He took out my eye.
And if I ever see him again,
I'm gonna cut open his head
and eat his brains!
You think he'd like that?
Can't kill him. He's
even meaner than you are.
But he's not here.
And he ain't coming.
And no one's gonna save you.
He'll come for me. He will.
Then you better tell me
what I wanna know
or he can see what's left
of you in a goddamn jar.
We're going to
die here, aren't we?
Aren't we?
After the atoll,
when I offered
myself to you,
why didn't you take me?
'Cause you didn't
really want me.
Not really.
Have I been asleep long?
I was dreaming.
It's funny.
I always thought
Dryland floated.
That it drifted with the wind.
That's why it was so hard to find.
Why did you believe
in it so much?
Because we weren't
made for the sea.
Got hands and feet.
We're supposed to walk.
I miss her sound.
Don't you?
GREGOR: Helen!
No, no, no.
Helen, up here. Above you!
(GREGOR GIGGLING GIDDILY)
HELEN: Gregor!
Smart thinking,
to burn your boat.
Without the smoke,
I never would have found you.
Who's that with you?
Ichthyus sapien,
is that really you?
I'll throw the rope down. You
catch it. I'll help you climb up.
Helen. Where's Enola?
Smokers took her. They'd have
me, too, if it weren't for him.
My friend, thank you.
Very human of you.
Go grab your things quickly.
Quickly. Come.
GREGOR: You see?
Right down there.
There's several of us survivors.
We'll just start over again.
MAN: You can't ask us
to go get her!
WOMAN 1: Enola's the reason
we're in all this trouble.
WOMAN 2: Forget it!
We're not going.
HELEN: They don't have any
reason to kill her.
They need to find Dryland
just like we do.
GREGOR: Of course.
HELEN: If the Mariner's
willing to go, why not us?
WOMAN 1: If he wants to go,
then let him!
WOMAN 2: We don't want you
here! You or the girl!
Helen. The papers
the Mariner brought you...
It's the same language
the tattoo is written in.
They're numbers.
MAN: Gregor, you're as crazy as she is!
WOMAN 1: We can't stay here!
We're wasting valuable time.
More Smokers will come.
We need to be moving now!
My friends, don't you see we need
this child if we want to find Dryland?
I'm not going.
Nobody is.
HELEN: We've seen
their smoke on the horizon!
Know what that is yet?
GREGOR: The numbers? Yes, I think I do.
It seems to be some ancient
form of geographic location,
latitude, longitude.
It doesn't make sense,
though.
The numbers, they seem to be
backwards or something.
It's upside down.
The world?
The poles have
reversed themselves?
I've been mapping
the cities below.
The world wasn't created in a
deluge. It was covered by it.
MAN: That's blasphemy!
No, it's true.
I've seen it with my own eyes. There
is land. It's right under our keel.
None of it's dry anymore.
Some is.
Enola's been there. I know
that now. I saw what she drew.
So that's why he's going
after Enola, to find Dryland.
I don't care about Dryland.
This is ridiculous.
Going after the Smokers?
He doesn't even know which
direction they came from.
MAN: I say let him go.
WOMAN 1: We're better
off without them anyway!
If she's alive,
I'll bring her back to you.
WOMAN 2: Forget the mute-o, Helen. If
he brings her back, they'll kill us!
I can't stand it. We gotta go help
him. I can't ask him to do this alone.
Oh, don't worry, my dear.
You're not going to have to.
You got that tattoo
figured out yet?
It would be easier
if it was flat, big and flat.
It needs to be flat.
What you got in mind?
Well, you cut it off her back.
You stretch it, mount it.
Give us a proper look.
DEACON: Take her down below until I holler.
Saint Joe, we're close.
After centuries of shame.
(PEOPLE SHOUTING IN DISTANCE)
They're getting ugly.
Don't I know it.
Announce me, cousin.
(CROWD CHANTING)
Hey. Here he is.
CROWD: Deacon!
Rise up,
brothers and sisters.
Turn your eyes
and open your hearts
to your humble benefactor,
your spiritual shepherd
and dictator for life,
the Deacon of the 'Deez.
(CROWD CHEERING)
(CROWD CLAMORING)
Deacon!
Children. Children
of the provider.
Citizens of the good ship.
Please, now, hear me speak.
I've had a vision.
MAN: Yeah, we're tired of your visions!
What about the land
you promised us?
ALL: Yeah!
DEACON: Oh, ye of little faith.
I've had a vision so great
that as it came to me, I wept.
And in this splenditudinous
figment of wonder...
Is that Bone's ride?
Is that blood on the seat?
... I saw.
And you know what it is
that I saw.
I saw the land.
(ALL CHEERING)
(MUFFLED SCREAMING)
(CROWD CHANTING)
Horse, that you?
(ENGINE REVVING)
Look, just bring it in slow,
okay? I don't have all day.
(ENGINE REVVING)
Horse!
Just bring it up slow.
I said slow! No, Horse!
Shouldn't be doing that.
You're gonna get in trouble.
That's right.
You're not afraid.
You've got your pet freak
coming to rescue you.
He's not a freak,
and he can take you anytime.
He's killed dozens of people, and he
doesn't have any mercy or anything.
He even kills little girls.
Haven't we all?
Shit.
It's Horse.
Find him. Find him!
Come on!
Yes! Yes! Yes!
Come on.
ENOLA: Getting nervous, aren't you?
I don't get nervous.
DEACON: And if there's
a river, we'll dam it.
And if there's a tree,
we'll ram it.
'Cause I'm talking
progress here.
Yes, sir.
I'm talking development.
Yeah!
For we shall suck and savor
the sweet flavor
of Dryland.
ENOLA: Face is all red.
Helen said with anybody
that has a face that red,
he's had too much sun
or too much to drink.
All right, that's it. I'm gonna
burn your face. Almost time.
What's up?
We're just talking
about her friend.
NORD: What's his name?
ENOLA: He doesn't have a name.
So death can't find him.
(MOCKING ENOLA'S TONE)
Doesn't have a home
or people to care for.
He's not afraid of anything,
men least of all.
He's fast and strong
like a big wind.
He can hear 100 miles
and see 100 miles underwater.
He can hide in the shadow
of the noon sun.
He could be right behind you, and you
won't even know it till you're dead!
Give it a rest.
He'll come for me. He will.
DEACON: We are the reason.
Yeah?
Well, I hope he does.
The Lord's creation.
Remember you said that.
DEACON: Look at us.
Look at us here today.
Yeah!
Dryland is not
just our destination,
but it is our destiny!
(ALL CHEERING)
Find him. Find him!
How can I find this
glorious place?
And he said to me,
"A child shall lead you. "
A child.
And behold!
It's time.
The instrument
of our salvation!
(CROWD CHEERING)
Our guide in the wild.
Our beacon in the darkness.
Turn her around, Nord.
She has shown me the path!
And before the holy-most
moment is upon us,
let's sacrifice one
to old Saint Joe.
And let's get this tub of shit
up to speed.
Yeah.
(MEN CHATTERING)
Pull!
Pull.
(MEN GRUNTING)
So which way we rowing?
I don't have a goddamn clue.
Don't worry.
They'll row for a month before
they figure out I'm faking it.
But why?
Oh, you want details.
Well, I'm not
telling these savages
that we haven't
solved the map yet.
I promised them results,
and I'll get them if I gotta
cut them out of her goddamn back.
Who is that?
Maybe one of
the spare rowers?
Why aren't you rowing?
It's him.
It is him.
You guys are in
so much trouble.
Well, I'll be damned.
It's the gentleman guppy.
You know, he's like a turd
that won't flush.
I want the girl.
You know, I thought
you were stupid, friend.
But I underestimated you.
You're a total
freaking retard.
(DEACON LAUGHS)
I want the girl. That's all.
Well, what on this screwed-up earth
makes you think you're gonna get her?
You know what this is?
I drop it, you burn.
We all burn.
Now, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Let's not do
anything rash here.
I mean, are you sure
she's worth all this?
She never does stop talking.
She never shuts up.
I noticed.
What is it, then?
It's the map.
She's my friend.
Golly gee. A single tear
rolls down my cheek.
I mean, you're gonna
die for your friend?
If it comes to that.
He's bluffing.
I'll kill him.
He's not bluffing.
He never bluffs.
Shut up!
I don't think you're gonna
drop that torch, my friend.
Why not?
Because you're not crazy.
No!
Oh, thank God.
(MAN SCREAMING)
(MACHINE GUN FIRING)
Look out!
That's him!
Let's go, God damn it!
Don't just stand there!
Kill something!
Was this your big vision?
I've always wanted
to drive this monster.
There he is! There he is!
That's him! There!
(SCREAMS)
ENOLA: Let me go! Let go!
Let go!
Let me go! Let go!
DEACON: Pilot!
Pilot!
Let me go!
Let go!
You should've stayed
underwater.
(CLICKING)
Now, you know how to fly an
airplane? You're lucky I do.
(SCREAMS)
Now, you stop it!
You behave yourself, now!
(EXPLOSION)
HELEN: It's going down.
You can see it sinking. Gregor,
bring us right down on top of it.
Hurry, Gregor!
GREGOR: Don't worry.
Hurry.
Enola! Up here!
Grab on!
GREGOR: Are they on yet?
GREGOR: What is it?
HELEN: I don't know!
Got you! I'm gonna rip
your cute little lungs out.
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
Pull! Almost.
(EXPLOSION)
(SCREAMS)
HELEN: No! Enola!
No!
Saint Joe. Hole in one.
Helen!
No! Enola!
GREGOR: Helen!
Hey! Hey!
HELEN: Oh, no! Quick!
What are we gonna do?
Tie this off.
Hurry! Tie it!
HELEN: Got it!
(SCREAMS)
(SCREAMING)
Get them up now.
(GREGOR LAUGHING)
GREGOR: Of course! North is south. What?
South is north.
I was swimming.
I saw.
GREGOR: My friends.
My friends, look.
If I take a bearing
from the sun
and reverse the coordinates
on Enola's back,
then Dryland is that way!
(SEAGULL CAWING)
(HELEN LAUGHING)
It's fresh!
All of this! It's fresh!
(HELEN WHOOPING)
(ALL LAUGHING)
I found something!
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
Maybe we should put them
under the dirt.
I think it was their way.
They must have known
they were dying.
(HELEN LAUGHING)
(WINDING)
(MUSIC PLAYING)
I'm home.
Where's the Mariner?
He was outside.
Wait. Wait!
I want to show you this.
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
(HORSES NEIGHING)
(HORSES GALLOPING)
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
First time in your life
you got nothing to say?
Enola, I have to go now.
But you came back for me.
I like you.
Why are you leaving?
I don't belong here. I belong
out there. You belong here.
It's too strange here.
It doesn't move right.
Helen said that
it's only landsickness.
We're all feeling it.
It'll go away soon.
It's more than that.